Guide to the George Augustus Sala Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Augustus Sala collection
1828-1942
1860-1895
GEN MSS 952
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
10.51
(26 boxes)
The George Augustus Sala Collection consists of papers accumulated by Ralph Straus in writing his biography of Sala; and autograph manuscript correspondence and writings by Sala acquired from other sources. Papers of Straus consist of autograph letters, signed, to and from Sala, members of his family, and others; autograph manuscript writings and notes by Sala; clippings of articles by and about Sala; photographs, engraved portraits, and printed caricatures of Sala; and autograph manuscript notes and correspondence of Straus.
Sala, George Augustus, 1828-1895
Straus, Ralph, 1882-1950
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ralph Straus Papers Relating to George Augustus Sala: purchased from Pickering and Chatto on the Plain Fund, 1946.
Materials from Other Sources: acquired from various sources, 1937-2005. For more information, see the finding aid container list.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Sala, George Augustus. Contributions to periodicals (Ip Sa31 C1 and Ip Sa31 +C1).
Sala, George Augustus. Pamphlets by and about George Augustus Henry Sala (Ip Sa31 1).
Other books owned by Sala may be found in the online catalog by searching "Sala, George Augustus" as a special collections subject or "Ip Sa31" as a local call number.
Drawings owned by Sala were transferred to theYale University Art Gallery in 1953.
George Augustus Sala (1828-1895)
English journalist; contributed to the Daily Telegraph and other serials; and published collections of his articles. Sala was a son of singer and actress Henrietta Catherina Florentina Simon Sala (1789?-1860). He married Harriet Elizabeth Hollingsworth Sala (died 1885) in 1859, and he married Bessie Stannard Sala in 1890.
Ralph Straus (1882-1950)
English author and journalist. Author of Sala: the Portrait of an Eminent Victorian (London: Constable, [1942]).
Scope and Contents
The George Augustus Sala Collection consists of papers accumulated by Ralph Straus in writing his biography of Sala; and autograph manuscript correspondence and writings by Sala acquired by the Library from other sources. Papers of Straus consist of autograph letters, signed, to and from Sala, members of his family, and others; autograph manuscript writings and notes by Sala; clippings of articles by and about Sala; photographs, engraved portraits, and printed caricatures of Sala; and autograph manuscript notes and correspondence of Straus.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Ralph Straus Papers Relating to George Augustus Sala, 1828-1942. II. Materials from Other Sources, 1855-1899.
Daily telegraph (London, England); Authors, English -- 19th century -- Archives; Authors, English -- 20th Century -- Archives; Journalism -- England; Journalists -- England; Engravings (prints) -- England -- 19th century; Photographs -- England -- 19th century; Authors -- England -- 19th century; Authors -- England -- 20th Century; Journalists -- England -- 19th century; Sala, Mrs. (Bessie); Sala, George Augustus, 1828-1895; Sala, Harriet Elizabeth Hollingsworth, -1885; Sala, Henrietta Catherina Florentina Simon, 1789?-1860; Sala family; Straus, Ralph, 1882-1950; Straus, Ralph, 1882-1950 ( Sala)
- Ralph Straus Papers Relating to George Augustus Sala, 1841-1942; Series I; 10.09; (15 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into four subseries: Correspondence, arranged by names of Sala and his family, and subarranged chronologically within each name; Writings by George Augustus Sala, arranged alphabetically by work title; Other Papers of George Augustus Sala, arranged alphabetically by folder title; and Other Papers of Ralph Straus, arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence consists of autograph letters, signed, from and to George Augustus Sala; Harriet Elizabeth Hollingsworth Sala; and Bessie Stannard Sala; and to Henrietta Catherina Florentina Simon Sala. Also present are typed transcripts of letters from George Augustus Sala, and third-party autograph letters, signed, concerning Sala. Writings of George Augustus Sala contains autograph manuscript drafts and clippings of articles and stories; autograph manuscript notes and fragments; and a disbound copy of Sala's autobiography, The Life and Adventures of George Augustus Sala (London: Cassell, 1895). Other Papers of George Augustus Sala contain additional writings fragments, family papers, and ephemera. Other Papers of Ralph Straus contains autograph manuscript notes, correspondence, and research materials. Original folders have been retained; additional fragments of notes by Straus, apparently concerning Sala, are affixed to some.
  - Correspondence
    - Sala, George Augustus
      Outgoing letters to:
      Allen, William, 1865; Appleton, G. Webb (George Webb), 1887; Archibald, E. M. (Edward Mortimer), 1864; Arnold [Edwin?], 1886; [Ashely, Sarah?], [1857]; Baccani, A., 1874-1882; Bennett, W. C. (William Cox), 1875; Beresford Hope, A. J. B. (Alexander James Beresford), 1862-1883; Berlyn, Peter, 1872; Birtles, J., 1871; Blackburn, Henry, 1871; Boehm, [Joseph Edgar, Sir?], 1881; Boehm, Louise Frances, 1881; Boshell, Mary, 1878; Boutcher, William, 1878; Bradley, Edward, Reverend, 1880; Bridgman, John, 1862; Bright, John, 1878; Brooks, Shirley, [1858?]-[1869?]; Brooks, Shirley, 1874; Buckstone, John Baldwin, 1868; Buckstone, [Isabella Copeland?], 1879, envelope only; Burnand, F. C. (Francis Cowley), 1894; Burrows, John Cordy, Sir, 1873
      Caley, T. Law, 1865; Caralampi, Madam, 1888; Cassell, Petter & Galpin, 1869; Chambers, J., 1874; Chapman, Frederic, [1859?]-1873; Chatto, Andrew, 1880; Christie, John, 1861; Clarke, Hyde, 1881; Clayton, Benjamin, 1853-1857; Colborne, Hon. Major, 1873; Cole, Henry, [1874?]-1881; Collins, Mortimer, 1870, envelope only; Collins, Wilkie, [1879]; Cooper, Thompson, 1882; Cornhill Magazine, 1860; Crowdy, James, 1882; Cruikshank, George, 1860-1877; Cruikshank, Eliza Widdison, 1876; Curzon, Frank, 1860
      Dallas, E. S. (Eneas Sweetland), 1877; Dalziel Brothers, 1878; Delaford, F. T., 1883; Dickens, Charles (1837-1896), 1869; Dicks, John, 1886; Dixon, William Hepworth, [1861?]-[1867]; Downing, Stuart, 1881; Draper, Edward, 1865; Edlin, Peter, Sir, 1891; Evans, W. R., 1872; Faithfull, Emily, 1878-1882; Finlay, Frank, 1877; Ford, Lieutenant Colonel, 1870; Gilbert, John, Sir, 1872; Gilbertson, E., 1879; Godwin, George, 1879; Gower, Ronald Sutherland, Lord, 1882
      Hallé, Charles, 1886; Hamilton, Walter, 1874-1882; Hancock, Laurence, 1890; Harrison, Ralph, [1888?]; Hay, Miss, 1882; Henty, G. A. (George Alfred), 1868; Hitchman, Master, 1891; Holdsworth, Edmund William Hunt, 1883; Hollingshead, John, 1879; Hood, Tom, 1871; Hooper, G. F., 1886; Hunt, Thornton Leigh [1872?]; Ingram, William, Sir, [1877]; Irving, Henry, Sir, 1880-1882; James, Daniel, 1884; Jennings, Louis J. (Louis John), 1879; Jopling, Mrs., 1886; Kenney, Charles Lamb, [1858]-1879; Kent, Charles, 1873-1882; Kerr, Edith, 1884; Kitton, Frederic George, 1884
      Lane, C. H., 1860; Latey, John, [1874?]-[1884]; Leland, Charles Godfrey, 1872-1887; Leslie, W., 1882; Levien, J., [1872?]; Lewis, Arthur, 1875, envelope only; Lindsay, Lady, 1879-1881; Lindsay, [Effie?], 1887; Loftus, Captain, [1885]; Loveday, H. J. (Henry J.), 1887; Lowe, Miss, 1882; Lowe, James, 1862; Lucas, Samuel, 1859; McMichael, T. C., 1881; Marshall, Julian, 1891; Mayhew, Mrs., [1869?]; Mayhew, Augustus, [1858]; Mayhew, Horace, 1859-1870; Melhuish, Frank H., 1893-1894; Menzies, Florence, 1886-1891; Mott, Mr., 1873; Murphy, J. Stormont, 1879-1884; Murray, T. Douglas, 1878; Newhall, Mrs., [1880?]; Nolan, W. M., 1883
      Palmer, C. S., 1882; Parry, [John?] W., Mrs., 1881; Payn, James, 1882; Payne, J. Bertand (James Bertrand), [1868?]; Pollock, Walter Herries, 1883-1890; Pollonnais, Gaston, 1860; Pond, Christopher, 1871; Pond, R[ichard?] R., 1856-[1862]; Pym, Horace N., 1878-[1879?], 1881, envelope only; Ravenscroft, Francis, 1874, envelope only; Redway, George, 1884; Reeves & Turner, 1881; Richardson, Benjamin Ward, 1877-1888; Roach, Reverend T., 1881; Robson, John, 1875, envelope only; Robson printingworks, [1877?]-1879, [1879?], 2 enveloped only; Rosenblatt, Julian, 1880; Ross, W. S. Joy, 1889; Russell, George William Erskine, 1884; Russell, William Howard, Sir, 1874-[1893?]
      Saturday Review, 1888; Scott, Clement, [1873]; Sharpe, Sutton, [1868?]; Sieveking, Edward H. (Edward Henry), 1879; Skirrow, Charles F., Mrs., 1878-[1887]; Skirrow, Charles F., Mr. and Mrs., 1884; Smith, George Barnett, 1882; Smith, G. Reeves, 1877; Smith, George, [1859?]; Smith, Mrs., 1875; Stapleton-Cotton, Miss, [1881?]; Story, [Ada Maud Broadwood?], [1891?], [1894]; Temple Bar, printer of, [1862], [1862]; Thompson, [Henry Yates?], 1881; Thomson, P. M., Mrs., 1860; Timmins, Samuel, 1881; Tinsley, William, 1865-[1870?]; Toole, John Lawrence, 1878-1886; Tout & Company, bookbinders, 1889; Train, George Francis [1860?]; Turner, Godfrey, 1873-1880
      Vizetelly, Henry, 1858-1859; Vizetelly, Miss, 1887; Ward, Edward Matthew, 1863-1878; West, W. A., 1854; Wills, William Henry, [1856]- 1863; Wilson, [1859]; Wood, J. S., 1881; Woolner, Thomas, 1878; Wright, A., 1890; Wrigley, Joseph, 1860; unidentified editors and others, about the funeral of Watts Phillips 1874; unidentified correspondents, 1862-1894.
      - Letters, 1853-1859; 3 (Box 1)
      - Letters, 1860-1862; 3 (Box 1)
      - Letters, 1863-1866; 2 (Box 1)
      - Letters, 1867-1869 (Box 1)
      - Letters, 1870-1872; 2 (Box 1)
      - Letters, 1873-1874; 2 (Box 1)
      - Letters, 1875-1876; 2 (Box 2)
      - Letters, 1877-1878; 3 (Box 2)
      - Letters, 1879; 2 (Box 2)
      - Letters, 1880-1881; 3 (Box 2)
      - Letters, 1882; 2 (Box 2)
      - Letters, 1883-1884; 2 (Box 3)
      - Letters, 1885-1886; 2 (Box 3)
      - Letters, 1887-1889; 2 (Box 3)
      - Letters, 1890-1895; 3 (Box 3)
    - Sala, George Augustus
      Incoming letters from:
      A'Becket, Arthur William, 1892-1894; Abercorn, James Hamilton, Duke of, 1976; Aberdeen and Temair, John Campbell Hamilton-Gordon, Marquess of, 1877; Aïdé, Hamilton, [1899?]; Alexander, George, Sir, 1890; Saxe-Coburg and Gotha, Alfred, Duke of, 1879; Armitage, Edward, 1872; Arnold, Edwin, 1870-[1891?]; Arnold, Julian, [1874-1878?]
      Bancroft, Marie; Bancroft, Squire, 12884; Barnum, P. T. (Phineas Taylor), 1890; Barrett, Wilson, 1882-1884; Bayard, Thomas F., 1894; Beatty-Kingston, W. (William), 1876, 1890; Bedford, Bessie, 1895; Bedford, John T., 1874-1881; Bellew, J. C. M. (John Chippendall Montesquieu), 1870; Besant, Walter, Sir, 1881-1890; Black, William, [1886?]-[1893?]; Blackwood, Helen, Lady, [1887?]; Blandford, Marquess of, [1882]; Braddon, M. E. (Mary Elizabeth), [1861?]-1886; Bradley, Edward, Reverend, 1886; Brake, William N., 1891; Brooks, Shirley, 1868-1874; Burdett-Coutts, Angela Georgina, 1881-1891; Burdett-Coutts, W. (William), 1881-1890; Burnaby, Fred, [1881?]; Burnaby, Lizzie, 1883; Burnand, F. C. (Francis Cowley), [1879?]-1889; Byron, Henry J. (Henry James), 1860-1882
      Churchill, Randolph Henry Spencer, Lord, 1894; Colam, John, 1879; Cole, Henry, Sir, 1875; Collins, Wilkie, 1879; Combermere, Mary Woolley Gibbings Cotton, Viscountess, [1879]-1887; Corelli, Marie, 1886; Cruikshank, Eliza Widdison, 1878; Cruikshank, George, 1868, [1875]; Daryl, Sidney, 1886; Delapryme, Charles, 1894; Dickens Charles (1837-1896), 1870-1894; Dilke, Charles Wentworth, Sir, 1879, 1890; Dixon, William Hepworth, 1878; Dresser, Christopher; Dufferin and Ava, Frederick Temple Hamilton-Temple-Blackwood, Marquess of, 1891-1895; Durham, George Frederick D'Arcy Lambton, Earl of, 1879
      Ebsworth, Joseph Woodfall, 1883; Faithfull, Emily, 1883; Fraser, William Augustus, Sir, 1879; Frith, William Powell, 1888; Fife, Alexander William George Duff, Duke of, [1881]-[1893?]; Gallenga, Antonio Carlo Napoleone, 1879; Gladstone, Helen, 1895; Gladstone, W. E. (William Ewart), 1895; Gower, Ronald Sutherland, Lord, 1887-1895; Grunerwald, Alice A., 1886; Grunerwald, Otto, 1886
      Hare, John Fairs, Sir, 1889; Hatton, Joseph, 1881; Hawkes, Charles P., 1893; Hennicker-Heaton, John, Sir, 1891; Herbert, Auberon, 1888; Herkomer, Hubert von, Sir, 1881; Hogarth, Edward, 1870; Hogarth, Georgina, 1878-1879; Hogarth, William, 1894; Hollingshead, John, 1869-1892; Hood, Tom, [1870]; Hunt, J. H., Reverend, 1875; Hunt, William Holman, 1880; Hyndman, H. M (Henry Mayers), 1891; Irving, Henry, 1880; James, Henry James, Baron, [1880]; Janson, Henry, 1887; Johnson, W. A., 1887; Jones, J. D., 1893; Kinnaird, Arthur, 1884; Knollys, Francis, 1895; Knox, Alexander, 1894
      Labouchers, Henry Du Pre, [1877], [1887?]; Lathom, Edward George Bootle Wilbraham, Earl of, 1882; Lefevere, Shaw, 1882; Le Gallienne, Richard, 1887; Leland, Charles Godfrey, 1874; Le Sage, John Merry, Sir, 1884; Lever, W. H., 1890; Lindsay, Effie Grout, [1887?]; Littledale, Ana, 1887; London, Brighton, and South Coast Railway, 1880; Lytton, Edward Robert Bulwer Lytton, Earl of, 1882
      McDonnell, Schomberg Kerr, Sir, 1889; Mackenzie, Morell, 1887; Macquoid, Thomas Robert, 1879; Malet, Edward, Sir, 1890-1891; Marlborough, George Charles, Duke of, [1884]; Marriott, Fred W., 1881; Marsden, Kate, 1891; Martineau, J. P., 1887; Mayhew, Athol, 1890; Mayhew, Augustus, 1873; Montalba, Clara, 1893; Moore, Sam, 1883; Morier, Robert, Sir, 1892; [Morocco?] Emperor of, [1880?]; Nattali, Miss M. H., [1882]-[1889?]
      O'Connor, Daniel, 1885; Ogilvie, George A., [1886?]; [Orton, Arthur?]; O'Rell, Max, 1893; Paul, Howard, 1873; Peel, Robert, 1884, 1889; Phillips, Alfred R., 1874; Phillips, Watts, [1872?]-[1873]; Pirbright, Henry de Worms, 1881; Pollock, Walter Herries, 1880-1881; Prior, Melton, 1894; Pym, Horace N., 1878; Quaritch, Bernard, 1879, 1882; Quigley, William T., 1887; Quilter, Harry, [1889?]
      Rabelais Club, 1882-1883; Rawson, C., 1894; Reade, Charles, [1872?], [188-?]; Reay, Fanny Georgiana Jane Hasler Mitchell, Baroness, 1884; Redford, George, 1890; Richmond, Charles Henry Gordon-Lennox, Duke of, 1879; Richmond, Harold W., 1895; Robertson, W. W., [1882?]; Rose, George, 1881; Rosebery, Archibald Philip Primrose, Earl of, 1879-1895; Roseberry, Hannah, Lady, 1883, 1888; Rothschild, Ferdinand, Baron, [1886?]; Russell, Charles, Sir, 1888; Russell, George William Erskine, [1886?]-[1890?]; Russell, William Howard, Sir, 1881-1890
      Satow, Y. Ernest, 1882; Scott, Clement, 1883; Shaw, Bernard V., 1881; Shaw, Eyre Masseym 1876; Soulsby, William, Sir, 1894; Spurgeon, C. H. (Charles Haddon), 1888-1889; Stephen, Leslie, 1889; Stevens, Henry, 1883; Stone, Marcus, 1870; Stout, Robert, 1886; Sutherland, George Grenville William, Duke of, [1892?]; Sympson, E. M., 1881; Taglionni, Marie, 1872; Taylor, W. Grigor, 1892; Terry, Ellen, Dame, 1887; Terry, Edward; Thaddeus, Henry Jones, [1893?]; Theodoli, Marchesa, 1893; Thorpe, B., Lieutenant, 1892; Tisdell, C. E., Reverend, 1892; Toole, John Lawrence, 1880, 1882; Turner, John, 1879
      Vaughn, Herbert, [1895?]; Volckman, W. and C., 1882; Wallace, Donald Mackenzie, 1887; Ward, Genevieve, 1875-1880; Watts, George Frederick, 1882; Whiteley, William, 1879; Williamson, Francis John, 1879; Winchilsea, Murray Edward Gordon Finch-Hatton, Earl of, 1882; Wolseley, Garnet Wolseley, Viscount, 1883, 1894; Wood, W. Charles, 1860; Woodville, Richard Caton, 1894; Wortley, Andrew S., 1892; Wright, Wm. Horace (William Horace), 1889; Wyndham, Charles, [1882?]; Yates, Edmund, 1877.
      - Letters, 1860-1873; 4 (Box 3)
      - Letters, 1874-1878; 4 (Box 4)
      - Letters, 1879-1880; 4 (Box 4)
      - Letters, 1881-1882; 4 (Box 4)
      - Letters, 1883-1886; 5 (Box 5)
      - Letters, 1887-1889; 4 (Box 5)
      - Letters, 1890-1892; 4 (Box 5)
      - Letters, 1893-1895; 5 (Box 6)
    - Sala, George Augustus
      Typed transcripts of outgoing letters.
      - Letters, typed transcripts, 1845-1864; 4 (Box 6)
      - Letters, typed transcripts, 1865-1874; 4 (Box 6)
      - Letters, typed transcripts, 1875-1879; 5 (Box 7)
      - Letters, typed transcripts, 1880-1882; 4 (Box 7)
      - Letters, typed transcripts, 1883-1886; 5 (Box 7)
      - Letters, typed transcripts, 1887-1895; 2 (Box 7)
    - Sala, Bessie Stannard
      Outgoing letters.
      - Andrews, William, 1891-1896 (Box 8)
      - Metcalf, R., 1890 July 9 (Box 8)
    - Sala, Bessie Stannard
      A'Beckett, Arthur William, 1891; Ashby-Sterry, J. (Joseph), 1891; Beatty-Kingston, W. (William), 1891; Besant, Walter, 1891, [1896?]; Black, William; Burdett-Coutts, Angela Georgina, 1890-1893; Burdett-Coutts, W. (William), 1891; Burnand, Francis Cowley, [1890?]; Camm, John, [1891?]; Farjeon, B. L. (Benjamin Leopold), 1891; Fife, Alexander William George Duff, Duke of, 1893; Hardwin, G. H. G., 1892; Hogarth, Georgina, 1898; Hollingshead, John, 1896; Hood, Alexander N., 1893; Jones, H.
      Le Sage, John Merry, Sir, 1892; Macnaughton (Henry Macnaughton), 1890; Marsden, [Kate?], 1891; O'Connor, Thomas P., 1892; Ponsonby, Mary, 1891; Ravosky, Sofia and Guilia, 1891; Rosebery, Archibald Philip Primrose, Earl of, 1896; Rowe, Robin, 1893; Sullivan, Arthur, [1892?]; Newnes, George, 1897; Stanley, Dorothy, Lady, 1890; Thaddeus, Henry Jones, [1893?]; Thompson, Henry, Sir, [1891?]; [Vanttier?], 1893; Warwick, Frances Evelyn Maynard Greville, Countess of, 1896; Williams, Montagu Stephen, 1890, [1892?]; Wolseley, Garnet Wolseley, Viscount, 1895-1896; Wood, J. S., 1890; Woodville, Richard Caton, Mrs., [1893?]; Wrighton, Fred, 1891; Wyndham, Charles, 1893.
      - Letters, 1890-1900; 5 (Box 8)
    - Sala, Harriet Elizabeth Hollingsworth
      Outgoing letter.
      - Cruikshank, Eliza Widdison, 1876 May 28 (Box 8)
    - Sala, Harriet Elizabeth Hollingsworth
      Burdett-Coutts, Angela Georgina, 1881; Collins, Frances, 1881; Hollingshead, John, 1878; Braddon, M. E. (Mary Elizabeth), 1877; Phillips, Caroline, undated.
      - Letters, 1872-1885 (Box 8)
    - Sala, Henrietta Catherina Florentina Simon
      - Lonsdale, Mr., 1856 January 15 (Box 8)
        Accompanied by a typed transcript.
      - Webster, Benjamin, 1841 May (Box 8)
    - Other letters relating to George Augustus Sala, 1872-1935; 3 (Box 8)
      Contents:
      Collins, Wilkie, to F. D. Finlay, 1879 November 7; Dickens, Charles (1837-1896), to F. D. Finlay, 1879 November; Forbes, Archibald, to [John Aitken?] Carlyle, [1872?]; Gedge, Sydney, to Eliza Widdison Cruikshank, 1878; Henty, G. A. (George Alfred), to Miss Bushnell, [1891?]; Hollingshead, John, to Illustrated London News, 1882 Janurary 6; Hollingshead, John, to F. D. Finlay, 1879 November 6; Hood, Alexander Nelson, Duke of Bronte, to G. Mildred, 1892 July 8; Hunt, William Holman, to Sir Edwin Arnold, 1889 May 7; Johnson, W. A. to Monsignor Stonor, 1887 December 28
      Mallet, Bernard, Sir, to Dr. William G. Thistle, 1896 July 17; Montefiore, Moses, Sir, to Illustrated London News, 1883 November 8; Norfolk, Henry Fitzalan-Howard, Duke of, to Mrs. Arthur Stannard, 1904 February 27; Otway, Arthur John, Sir, to Mrs. Arthur Stannard, [1904?] February 25; Paget, Augustus Berkeley, Sir, to E. Lynn (Elizabeth Lynn) Linton, [1891?] February 17; Salisbury, Robert Cecil, Marquess of, to Alexander William George Duff, Duke of Fife, 1896 February 21; Taylor, Arnold, to John Morely, Viscount Morely, 1880 July 15; Thistle, Dr.William G. to Ernest Alfred Vizetelly, 1895 November 13; "Toby" to unidentified, [1897?].
  - Writings by George Augustus Sala
    - Breakfast in Bed. "On a Little Boy Going to School," autograph manuscript fragment, 1862 (Box 8)
      Published in Temple Bar, 1862 November.
    - "Buffalo Bill," clippings, 1887 (Box 8)
    - Banquets, burials and other functions: articles published in The Daily Telegraph, clippings, 1874; 4 (Box 9)
    - "The Byron statue and other papers," clippings, 1880; 2 (Box 9)
    - "The Death of Charles Dickens," clippings, 1870 (Box 9)
    - Dutch Pictures. "The Conversion of Colonel Quagg," autograph manuscript, 1851-1860 (Box 9)
    - Gaslight and Daylight. "How I went to sea," autograph manuscript fragment, 1851-1856 (Box 9)
      Original title: "On Tramp."
      Published in Household Words, 1852 October 2.
    - "Gerald Moreland, or, the Forged Will," autograph manuscript, 1842; 2 (Box 10)
      Includes 3 pen-and-ink illustrations by Sala.
      With dedication to Sarah E. Ashley, Sala's cousin, and autograph manuscript note, 1876 July 28, stating that the manuscript was returned to him by his cousin 34 years after it was completed.
    - "Gerald Moreland, or, The Forged Will," typed transcript, undated; 2 (Box 10)
    - The Life and Adventures of George Augustus Sala (London: Cassell, 1895)
      Disbound copy.
      - Volume I, pages i-112, 1895; 4 (Box 10)
      - Volume I, pages 113-224, 1895; 4 (Box 10)
      - Volume I, pages 225-336, 1895; 4 (Box 11)
      - Volume I, pages 337-442, 1895; 3 (Box 10)
      - Volume II, pages i-112, 1895; 4 (Box 11)
      - Volume II, pages 113-224, 1895; 4 (Box 11)
      - Volume II, pages 225-336, 1895; 3 (Box 12)
      - Volume II, pages 337-457, 1895; 4 (Box 12)
    - Mormons and Mountebanks: articles published in The Daily Telegraph, clippings, 1881; 4 (Box 12)
    - "Mr. Quedlingburg's Commission," autograph manuscript, 1863 (Box 12)
    - Stories with a Vengeance. "The Good Young Man" and "The Demon Piano," autograph manuscript, 1877-1881 (Box 13)
      Published in Bow Bells Annual, 1877-1878.
    - The Streets of the World. "Berlin: Unter Den Linden" and "Windsor: Thames Street," autograph manuscript, 1864 (Box 13)
      Published in Temple Bar, 1864 April -May.
    - "The Toy Frigate," autograph manuscript and clipping, 1873 (Box 13)
      Originally title: "Captain Lemonkyd's Yacht."
      Published in London Society, The Christmas Number, "Rabagorn, or, the Princess Sweetie and her Pet Parrot," 1873
    - "William Hogarth," clippings, Cornhill Magazine, 1860; 4 (Box 13)
    - Other Writings
      - Exercise book, circa 1842-1843; 3 (Box 13)
        Excerpts from other writers, apparently copied by Sala as a child.
      - Hotten, John Camden. The Slang Dictionary (London: Chatto and Windus, 1874). Notes, autograph manuscript (Box 14)
        Disbound copy with notes by Sala.
      - Lecture in Melbourne on his war-time experiences, autograph manuscript and printed, 1885 (Box 26 (Oversize))
      - Other writings and fragments, autograph manuscript, 1848-1871, undated; 2 (Box 14)
        Notebook, 2 pages, 1848.
        "The Girl I Left Behind Me," fragment, 1 page. Published in Household Words, 1854 April 1.
        Article, fragment. Published in The Illustrated Times, [1863 May?].
        "William Hogarth," 1 page.
        "Seven Sons of Mammon," 1 page.
        Prospectus for The International Literary and General Advertising Company, 2 pages.
        Notes, anthropology and physiology, 1 page.
        "The Vision of the Sword," 1 page, [Rome, 1866].
        "Poste Restante," 2 pages. Published in All the year round, 1869 January 23, and Under the Sun.
        "General Bunkum's Opinion of the Autumn Campaign," 2 pages. Published in Fun, 1871 October 7.
        "The Policeman's Complaint," poem, 1 page. Published in Fun, 1871 November 4.
      - Other writings and fragments, autograph manuscript, 1873-1890, undated; 2 (Box 14)
        Article on the history of the Jews, draft, 2 pages, 1873 July 29.
        Article on Bulwer Lytton, notes, 1 page, [1873 January].
        Article on mythology, notes, 3 pages, 1873 August 4.
        Notes for an article, 1 page, with clipping. [1873?].
        Notes about the Cantebury Tales, 1 page, [1873?].
        Notes for articles, 1 page, 1873 September 20.
        Notes for articles, 2 pages, [1873].